Guide to the A. C. Greene Papers
The Wittliff Collections
A. C. Greene Papers
1967-1969, 1973
The Wittliff Collections
Greene, A. C., 1923-2002
SWWC.017
214
1 boxes
.5 Linear Feet
Seven folders of works, published materials, photographs, correspondence, cards, and programs highlight the work of A.C. Greene.
Scope and Contents
Seven folders of works, published materials, photographs, correspondence, cards, and programs highlight the work of A.C. Greene. The collection has been divided into three series: Works (1967, 1969, 1973, undated), Photographs (1968), and Cards and Programs (1969, undated). The bulk of the collection consists of manuscripts collected by Bill Wittliff. Multiple drafts of the essay "Paisano" are included in one folder, following the work from annotated typewritten draft to television script to published work. Also of note are screenplays that Greene adapted from his books The Last Captive and The Santa Claus Bank Robbery. The collection includes published magazine articles, photographs, and cards and programs relating to Greene.
Conditions Governing Access
Collection is open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donation from Bill Wittliff and A.C. Greene from 1988 to 1993.
Biographical Notes
Alvin Carl Greene (1923-2002) was born and raised in Abilene, Texas. He left Texas during World War II and served in the U.S. Navy and Marines. After a four-year stint in the military, Greene received a B.A. from Abilene Christian College in 1948 and began working as a reporter for the Abilene Reporter-News. He remained on the staff for 12 years and also ran a bookstore in Abilene from 1952 to 1957.
In 1960, Greene joined The Dallas Morning News as book editor and editorial columnist. Eight years later he left to concentrate on writing and received a Dobie-Paisano fellowship which allowed him to finish his acclaimed book, A Personal Country, in 1969. Greene went on to publish many books and articles in the 1970s and 1980s. The range of Greene's writing has been very broad, although he is closely tied to the subject of Texas. His books cover cities in Texas, historical events in the nineteenth and twentieth centuries, personal reminiscences, and literary criticism. He also worked at KERA-TV in Dallas as news commentator from 1970 through 1977 and has reviewed books for the MacNeil/Lehrer News Hour. Greene taught journalism at Hardin-Simmons University, The University of Texas at Austin, and Southern Methodist University, and served as Coordinating Director of the Center for Texas Studies at the University of North Texas in Denton.
Health problems in the late 1980s kept him from writing, but after receiving a heart transplant Greene recovered and published a book, Taking Heart, about his illness. Greene was a member of PEN International, the Writers Guild of America, and the Texas Institute of Letters. He passed away in 2002.
Authors, American -- Texas -- 20th century; American journalists; Historians -- Texas; Greene, A. C., 1923-2002
- Works, 1967, 1969, 1973, undated
  - "Paisano," draft of essay, television script, and published pamphlet, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Essays, includes television script of piece on Luckenbach, Texas, "Appreciating the Diversity of Texas" (a speech delivered at the Texas State Historical Association Meeting), an essay on J. Frank Dobie, the original draft of "The Highland Park Woman," and a television copy of a story about Christmas, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - "The Deadly Season," a screenplay based on the book The Santa Claus Bank Robbery, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - "The Last Captive," carbon of submitted script, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Magazine and journal articles, includes "God in West Texas," in The Arlington Quarterly (Autumn 1967), "The Durable Society: Austin in the Reconstruction," in The Southwestern Historical Quarterly (April 1969), and "The Perfect Christmas," in McCall's (December 1973), 1967, 1969, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Photographs, 1968
  - Photos of Greene taken while he was the second Paisano fellow, February 1968 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Cards and programs, 1969, undated
  - Program from the Amon Carter Museum of Western Art (1969) and a Christmas card, 1969, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)